CSRFs used to be a really popular bug class,
but then browser developers did something really smart
and they introduced a cookie attribute called SameSite
that was supposed to prevent these vulnerabilities.
But did it really kill CSRFs?
Can you still get good bounties for CSRFs in 2024?
Well, there's only one way to find out,
to do the case study, and so I did.
In this video, I will tell you what techniques
still work in 2024 and how you can still get
good bounties for CSRFs.
Enjoy.
And the first label that I have in this category
is very optimistic for the future of CSRFs
because in 38 reports, I decided that the SameSite cookie
would not, SameSite lags to be more precise,
would not help because the request with CSRF
was using the get method.
And there were a few different types of attacks here,
different types of get requests.
I broke this down in the other part of the case study
that's in BBRE Premium Archive, but for example,
it was a report like this one in Facebook
where the hunter would send a get request,
that wouldn't directly make any modifications on the server,
but it would cause the client-side JavaScript
to immediately, without any user interaction,
send the request to the server.
And this request done by JavaScript would be a POST request
and it would have the proper CSRF token and everything,
but the attacker would control the path of this request
and potentially parameters as well.
So the attacker would control everything,
the client-side JavaScript would automatically append
the CSRF token.
And in this case, SameSite attribute with the lag setting
or with the strict, to be honest as well, does not help you.
And this report, it was submitted in 2022
when SameSite was already working.
It was $18,750.
So quite a good report.
We see that Facebook, I think, has problems
with these types of CSRFs because,
take a look at how many Facebook reports we have here.
That's eight reports, a few of them in five-digit bounties.
So quite an important backlash.
The next category that I found here
was before SameSite defaulting to lags,
because if we take a look at the CSRF reports by year,
SameSite attribute was introduced in Chrome back in 2016,
but for four years, it was pretty irrelevant
because only Chrome supported it
and also developers had to actively implement this,
which developers are not really eager
to implement new defense mechanisms
until they have to.
And it makes a lot of sense from the business perspective.
And in this period, you couldn't even properly recommend
SameSite cookie as a CSRF prevention
because it only worked in Chrome.
So for four years, it was quite irrelevant.
Then in 2020, Chrome started defaulting to lags
when the SameSite attribute was not present.
And then Firefox followed up in 2021.
And that's when the SameSite attribute started
become relevant.
And today, it's quite a fundamental part
of the client-side security.
For example, in this category,
we had maybe reports like this one.
It's also in Facebook.
And that's a pretty standard post request
where the cookie has to be attached
for this request to work.
And with SameSite lags, a cross-site request like this
just wouldn't have the cookies automatically appended.
There is one catch to it.
It's a two-minute attack window,
but more on this in the later chapter
because I have a separate category for that kind of report.
Now we'll jump to the next category
or the next two categories that I have here
are where SameSite attribute was unmentioned,
but it was already in this period where it was relevant.
To be precise, 11 reports
where when only Firefox would not default to lags,
when Chrome would already default to lags,
when SameSite was not present, but Firefox didn't.
In this period, you could always write in the report
that this CSRF would be mitigated
by the SameSite attribute,
but it still works in Firefox.
And there was one report like this.
It was in Atlassian.
And let's not get into details of this particular bug,
but the hunter did write that due to the SameSite behavior,
it doesn't work in Chrome.
It only works in Firefox.
And props to this hunter.
He got 3.6 thousand dollars for this report
and to authors of these 22 reports
which didn't mention the SameSite attribute,
shame on you, to be honest.
I think every single CSRF report after 2020
should mention the SameSite attribute.
No matter if SameSite cookie will be appended,
it won't be appended, why it won't be appended,
doesn't matter which outcome it is,
you should always address this in your report
because it just first,
it solves a lot of problems with the triage.
I'm 100% confident that in at least a few of these reports,
there was a case that the report only worked in Firefox,
the hunter only used Firefox,
but the triager used Chrome and it didn't work
so they would go back and forth with the report.
I'm 100% sure there was a case like this.
If you address those things straight away,
you will just get better bounties.
You know, always when doing these case studies,
I start with the highest-paid reports
and I go to the lowest-paid reports
and I always, in every single case study,
I see the same trend that the highest-paid reports
always, in general, mention every single aspect of a bug,
every single prevention mechanism that could affect the bug
but maybe it can be bypassed in one way or another
and then the further I go,
the more rare it is for hunters to mention it.
Maybe they don't know about it.
Maybe they just try to avoid the difficult conversation
about the same side attribute
but definitely it shows that if you understand
more aspects of web security,
you will get bigger bounties.
Then the next category, I have six reports
where it was explicitly said
that the same-side cookie was none.
Four of these reports are in Google
and one of these I did cover on my channel.
It's a CSRF by David Schutz, which I really liked.
He kind of made, exploited the TV version of YouTube
to leak private videos of the victim
and he got a CSRF like this.
It's a great report.
I will link the video and the report in the description.
To be perfectly fair,
this report could also go to the previous category
because this article does not mention
the same-side attribute at all
but I know that same-side cookie was set to none
because I just asked David before making the video
and I think because he mostly hacked on Google
and Google, at least back then,
used same-side none everywhere,
he just didn't consider same-side cookie
as the relevant for this report
and while for me it was like, why does this work?
But he sent me a screenshot where it was same-side nones
and that's why I know about this.
Then we have two more categories with one report each
because the bug only works in Firefox.
I already have shown you.
The first case is something
that maybe shouldn't be here, if I'm honest,
but it's a report that I really like
and I wanted to have it in at least one of the case studies
and it wouldn't fit anywhere better than it fits to CSRFs.
It's a bug by Johan Carlsson
which I also covered on my channel.
It's a client-side path traversal
and the way it works is that in one of the places,
instead of a regular ID,
you are injecting a dot dot slash character
which is typical for path traversals
but what happens here, it's on the client-side
and then when the victim would press,
in this case, this button to resolve
or ignore an issue, I think, or an error,
then the put request would be sent
with a proper CSRF token.
It would actually be a same-side request
and because you would control the path of this request
and you also could inject URL query parameters
and Rails is known to treat these URL query parameters
pretty much the same way as the put body or the post body,
you would just control the path
and attributes of the request
so you would have sort of a site-wide CSRF.
The reason why I think it doesn't quite fit
to the CSRF category is it ends up being a same-side request
and CSRF stands for cross-site request forgery
and this isn't really a cross-site request
but I think it somehow fits to the CSRF category.
That's why I wanted it here
and one more reason for having it here
is I think it is a bug class
with a lot of potential for the future
because a lot of applications these days
do a lot of work with the client-side JavaScript
and I think bugs like this will only become more common
and in cases where you can't find regular CSRFs,
you should be looking for client-side path traversals
so that's also a reason why I wanted to include this bug.
If you didn't quite get it from my quick explanation now,
the link to the full video
and the link to the report are in the description
and the last thing I have
but the very important thing I have
is this $3,000 report in Yahoo
and the reason why I think it is very important
is because the whole video
about same-side cookie defaulting to lags,
I'm saying you that if there's no same-side attribute,
the browser defaults as it would be same-side lags
but Chrome only does it
after two minutes from setting the cookie
and this is very, very important
because it means after setting the cookie,
you have the two-minute attack window
where the cookie works as it worked before.
In this case, the hunter, I'm surprised,
this is the only report
where the hunter explicitly mentioned
exploiting this two-minute attack window
and the reason I mentioned it
is the 33 reports I showed you before
that I told you that maybe these reports
would be mitigated by this mechanism
and they wouldn't work today.
This is the only sort of scenario
where you could still exploit those CSRFs
and now the question you might have,
two minutes after the login is not a lot of time
and you would be right
but when I'm saying two minutes after setting the cookie,
it is not the same as two minutes after the login
because cookies are not only set after the login.
You know, cookies are rotated all the time
and even if I'm logged into a website
for days, for weeks maybe,
probably my cookies are being changed a lot
and when you have a CSRF
which does rely on this two-minute attack window,
you should also try to find scenarios
where you can force the cookie to be refreshed.
For example, if after opening the main page of the website,
maybe cookies get refreshed.
Maybe if a logged in victim opens a login panel,
maybe then their cookies get rotated
but they remain logged in.
You should seek scenarios like this
because then you can just open
this two-minute attack window yourself
and in this context, two minutes is a lot of time
to carry out the CSRF.
So I think the three most important takeaways for you
from this whole video is first,
pay attention to GET requests.
If they, in one way or another,
can cause some changes on the server,
the second thing you should pay attention to
is the two-minute attack window in Chrome.
I think it doesn't work like this in Firefox
and I don't know for how much longer
it will work like this in Chrome
and the third thing is obviously,
pay attention to same-site non-cookies
because same-site can break some things,
especially if you want functionality
like embedding your YouTube videos on other websites.
Same-site breaks this functionality
so look for this.
If you're interested in more specific types of these things,
check out the full case study in BBRE Premium Archive
and if you are not a member of BBRE Premium yet,
I recommend you this free video about IDOR case study.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye.